(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-08-21T14:20:14.691473",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
ゼロ
Zero!
ポルカ！オルカ！ポルカ！オルカ！
Polka! Polka! Polka! Polka!
みんな！今日は
Everyone, today
尾丸ポルカ生誕祭2023に来てくれて、ありがとー！
thank you for coming to Omaru Polka's 2023 Birthday Festival!
というわけでこちら、ハッシュタグが、えーと、こちらになっております。
So as you can see, the hashtag is right over here.
ここらへんでてる、でてる、お、でてる。うん、でてるでてる。ありがとうございます。
It's showing up around here... Oh, it's there. Yep, it's there. Thank you!
えー、特別なね、この日にね、最高のゲストも呼んでおりますので、
Um, since we've invited some amazing guests for this special day—
あ、あのさっきちょっとね、声が聞こえ、だから、
Oh, earlier my voice sounded a bit... that's why!
はい、というわけでね、えー、見てるみんなも、それ以外のひとも
Anyway, so for everyone watching and anyone else joining in—
楽しんでいただけるように、え？それ以外って誰だ？まあいいや、
wait, who's "anyone else"? Oh well, hold on,
ちょっと待て、ゲストの人ちょっと助けてもらおう。
let me get some help from the guests.
えーそれでは呼んでみましょう！ゲストの人どうぞー！
Well then, let's call them out! Guests, please come on in!
おー！いらっしゃい！いらっしゃい！いらっしゃい！いらっしゃい！
Whoa! Welcome, welcome, welcome, welcome!
いらっしゃい！いらっしゃい！いらっしゃい！いらっしゃい！
Welcome, welcome, welcome, welcome!
やったー！おめでとー！
Yay! Happy birthday!
よかったよかった！止まってくれてよかった、よし。
So glad it worked out! I'm so glad it stopped, phew.
ポルカの息も止まって
Polka's breath almost stopped too—
大丈夫、大丈夫？ポルカ大丈夫？
Are you okay? Polka, are you okay?
よっしゃ、おめでとー！これで頑張れるぜ！
Alright! Happy birthday! I can do my best now!
お水も飲んで、ポルカじゃあ。
Drink some water, Polka.
お水のもう？こんなみじかいときにもう出る？
Drink water? Already coming out at a time like this?
ちょっとみおしゃ、すごいなこのトークで。
Mio-sha, your talk game is amazing.
そうなんだね、それどうやってできんの？
Is that so? How do you even do that?
それ何？
What is that?
どうやってのそれ？すごーい。
How do you do that? That's amazing!
今日は、あ、こういうこなれたトーク？ うん、まあ、一応まあそれは置いといて
Today... Oh, this seasoned talk? Well, putting that aside for a moment—
え、今日は特別なゲストの方にね、ええときていただきます。まずはみおしゃ！ありがとう本当に来てくれて！
Today we have special guests joining us! First off, Mio-sha! Thank you so much for coming!
ありがとう呼んでくれて！お誕生日おめでとう！
Thanks for having me! Happy birthday!
おめでとー！おめでとうー！よかったねー！
Happy birthday! Congratulations! So great!
じゃ、すばちゃん！ありがとう来てくれて！おめでとう！
And Subaru-chan! Thanks for coming! Congrats!
早口やな！何言ってるか聞き取れんかったわ！
That was fast! I couldn't understand a single word!
そして、姫！
And, Hime!
にゃーい！ありがとう！ポルカのおめめちゅるちゅるー！かわいい！
Nya-i! Thank you! Polka's eyes are all sparkly! So cute!
かわいいねー！じゃあ、なんかね、ゲスト達と一緒に歌って、おしゃべりしていきたいと思います！
So cute! Now, we'd like to sing and chat together with our guests!
おめでとー！みんなも盛り上がってくれるようにハッシュタグね、これね。
Congrats! Everyone, make sure to get hyped and use the hashtag, okay?
はい、これね、つけてください。お願いします！
Yes, please use this one. Thank you!
尾丸ポルカ生誕祭2023！お、よろしくお願いします！お願いいします！
Omaru Polka Birthday Festival 2023! Thank you so much! Please!
さっそく歌っていこうと思うぜ！みんなもう一緒に行きたいからね、えーと。
Let's start singing right away! We all want to go together, so uh...
あ、姫！姫から行きましょう！まずはね！
Ah, Hime! Let's start with Hime! First up!
姫とポルカで歌わせていただきます！1番目でいいなら。
Hime and Polka will sing! If it's fine being first.
1番目でいいならね。みおしゃ、じゃあね！
If 1st is okay. Mio-sha, see ya!
じゃあね！またね！がんばって！
See ya! Bye! Do your best!
雑談な！え、姫、大丈夫？今日はしっとり歌える？
Chatting! Um, Hime, are you okay? Can you sing emotionally today?
頑張るの！しっとり行くぜ！でできるもんね！
I'll do my best! We're going emotional! We can do it!
おいら、いっぱいいっぱいがんばって歌うの！任せて！多分大丈夫な気がする。
I'll do my absolute best to sing! Leave it to me! I think it'll probably be fine.
よし、じゃあ...
Alright, then...
夕日が落ちる様に胸が染まるので
As the setting sun dyes my chest,
耳鳴りのような鼓動を隠して
I hide my heartbeat, like a ringing in my ears.
バスに乗った僕は言う
And from the bus, I say:
君は灰になって征く
"You'll turn to ashes and fade away."
たとえばこんな言葉さえ失う言葉が僕に言えたら
If I could find the words to say what can't be said,
灯籠の咲く星の海に心臓を投げたのだ
I would cast my heart into a starlit sea of glowing lanterns.
もう声も出ないそれは僕じゃどうしようもなかったのだ
My voice is gone—there was nothing I could do.
悲しくもないし苦しくもないのに
It's not sad, nor is it painful,
辛いと思うだけ 辛いと思うだけ
yet it hurts just to think about it.
古びたバス停の端 傘を持った僕がいる
Standing at the edge of an old bus stop, holding my umbrella,
今でさえ埃を被った夜空の隅に足は着くのに
even now, my feet touch the dusty corner of the night sky,
心臓が痛いから死んだふりの毎日を見なよ
yet my heart aches—look at me pretending to be dead every single day.
もういっそ死のうと思えたなら僕はこうじゃなかったのだ
If only I could just decide to die, I wouldn't be like this.
どうせ死ぬくせに辛いなんておかしいじゃないか
It's strange to say it's hard when you're going to die anyway.
灯籠の咲く星の海に
Into a starlit sea of lanterns,
心臓を投げたのだ
I threw my heart.
もう声も出ないそれは
My voice is gone,
僕じゃどうしようもなかったのだ
and there was nothing I could do.
悲しくもないし苦しくもないのに
It's not sad, nor is it painful,
辛いと思うだけ 辛いと思うだけに
yet it hurts just to think about it...
散らばった糸を思うだけ 散らばった糸を思うだけに
I just think of scattered threads...
古びたバス停の端 傘を持った僕がいる
Standing at the edge of an old bus stop, holding my umbrella,
今でさえ埃を被った夜空の隅に
even now, in the corner of the dusty night sky...
心臓が痛いから死んだふりの毎日を見なよ
My heart aches—look at me pretending to be dead every single day.
もういっそ死のうと思えたなら
If only I could just decide to die,
僕はこうじゃなかったのだ
I wouldn't be like this.
どうせ死ぬくせに辛いなんておかしいじゃないか
It's strange to say it's hard when you're going to die anyway.
だから愛さえできないこんな世界の色に僕の歌を混ぜて
That's why I mix my song into the colors of this loveless world,
もうどうしたいと思うくせに僕はどうもしないままで
and though I want to do something, I stay doing nothing at all.
灯籠の咲く星の海に心臓を投げたのだ
I threw my heart into a starlit sea of lanterns.
もう声も出ないから死んだふりなんてどうもなかったのに
My voice is gone, so pretending to be dead shouldn't have mattered,
君がずっと遠く笑ったのだ
yet you just kept smiling far away.
Daphne
Ficus
Iris
Maackia
Lythrum
Myrica
Sabia
Flos
拝啓 僕の願いよ 未来よ
To whom it may concern, my wish, my future...
絶え間無い後悔よ
endless regrets.
体感八度五分の夢は散らばってしまった
The sensational dream of 8.5 degrees has scattered away.
再啓 君の想いは 憂いは
Re-disclosed, your feelings, your worries...
Daphne
Ficus
Iris
Maackia
Lythrum
Myrica
Sabia
Thymus
Ribes
Abelia
Sedum
Felicia
Ochna
Lychnis
Flos
冴え渡る君の想いは 腕は
Your clear feelings, your arms...
巡る感情論だ
are a revolving theory of emotions.
半径八十五分の世界に
In a world with a radius of 85 minutes...
縛られたまま
Bound up,
本音を差し違えた今日を
Today, when we crossed our true feelings,
溢れた一切に
Overflowing into everything,
薪を焼べて風に乗せて錆びた空を彩る
Burn the firewood, ride the wind, and paint the rusted sky.
燻んだ日々を丁寧に
Tending carefully to these hazy days,
飾った花は直ぐに枯れてく
The flowers we decorated wither away at once.
愚鈍な僕は夢から覚めて
Foolish me, waking up from a dream,
綴った意味も無い無い無いな
Finding no meaning in what I wrote down...
君が僕にくれた声も色も 揺るぎない愛も
The voice, the color, and unwavering love you gave me...
二人きりの空に光った星も とうに散ってしまった
And the stars that shone in our lonely sky have long since scattered.
難儀の果てのモノクロの部屋に 季節は色褪せて
In this monochrome room at the end of hardship, the seasons fade,
熱を帯びて身悶んで擦れた体にこぼるる
Overflowing from a body writhing with heat and friction.
燻んだ日々を丁寧に 辿った先に花が咲くはず
Tending carefully to hazy days, flowers should bloom at the end of the road.
理屈な君は夢を見たまま 悟った振りで水を注いだ
Clever you, still dreaming, pretended to understand and poured water.
木漏れ日の下に 柔らまく咲いた花は
Flowers blooming softly beneath the sunbeams...
雲の上で違う星で 夢の先で揺れてる
Swaying above the clouds, on a different star, beyond the dream.
燻んだ日々を丁寧に 飾った花は直ぐに枯れてく
Tending carefully to hazy days, the flowers we decorated wither away at once.
愚鈍な僕は夢から覚めて 綴った意味も無い無い無いな
Foolish me, waking up from a dream, finding no meaning in what I wrote down...
不毛な日々を丁寧に 綴った紙に花を描いた
Tending carefully to barren days, I drew flowers on the paper I wrote.
不遇な僕ら夢に破れて 誓った筈も無かったことにした
Unfortunate us, defeated by our dreams, pretending we never swore anything.
Daphne
Ficus
Iris
Maackia
Lythrum
Myrica
Sabia
Thymus
Ribes
Abelia
Sedum
Felicia
Ochna
Lychnis
Daphne
Ficus
Iris
Maackia
Lythrum
Myrica
Sabia
Daphne
Ficus
Iris
Maackia
Lythrum
Myrica
Sabia
Thymus
Ribes
Abelia
Sedum
Felicia
Ochna
Lychnis
Daphne
Ficus
Iris
Maackia
Lythrum
Myrica
Sabia
Flos
サイレントマジョリティー
[Song: Silent Majority]
人が溢れた交差点を どこへ行く?
Where are you going at the overflowing intersection?
似たような服を着て 似たような表情で
Wearing similar clothes with similar expressions...
胸の中に紛れるように 歩いている
Walking as if blending into the crowd.
誰かと違うことに 何をためらうのだろう
What makes us hesitate to be different from others?
先行く人が振り返り 列を乱すなと
The people ahead turn back and tell us not to break the line.
ルールを説くけれど その目は死んでいる
They preach the rules, but their eyes are dead.
君は君らしく生きて行く自由があるんだ
You have the freedom to live life your own way.
大人たちに支配されるな
Don't let the adults control you.
始めから そう諦めてしまったら
If you give up right from the start,
僕らは何のために生まれてきたのか
what were we born for?
夢を見ることは 時には孤独にもなるよ
Sometimes, dreaming can be lonely,
誰もいない道を 進むんだ
walking down a path where no one else is.
この世界は 群れていても 始まらない
Even if this world flocks together, nothing begins.
Yesでいいのか? サイレントマジョリティー
Is a 'Yes' okay? Silent Majority
どこかの国の偉い政治家が 言っていた
An important politician in some country said,
声を聞かないものたちは 賛成していると…
that those who don't raise their voices are in favor...
選ぶことが大事なんだ 人に任せるな
Choosing is important, don't leave it to others.
行動しなければ 何も伝わらない
If you don't act, nothing will be conveyed.
君は君らしく やりたいことをやるだけさ
You should just be yourself and do what you want to do.
One of themに成り下がるな
Don't stoop to becoming 'one of them'.
ここにいる人の数だけ 道はある
There are as many paths as there are people here.
自分の夢のほうに 歩けばいい
You just need to walk toward your own dream.
見栄やプライドの 鎖に繋がれたような つまらない大人とは置いていけ
Leave behind those boring adults chained by vanity and pride.
さあ 未来は君たちのためにある
Come on, the future is for you.
No!と言いなよ! サイレントマジョリティー
Say 'No'! Silent Majority
誰かの後を付いて行ければ 傷つかないけど
If you follow someone's lead you won't get hurt,
その群れが総意だと 一まとめにされる
but that crowd is lumped together as the consensus.
君は君らしく 生きていく自由があるんだ
You have the freedom to live life your own way.
大人たちに支配されるな
Don't let adults control you.
初めから そう諦めてしまったら
If you give up from the very beginning like that,
僕らは何のために 生まれたのか?
what were we born for?
夢を見ることは 時には孤独にもなるよ
Sometimes, dreaming can be lonely,
誰もいない道を 進むんだ
walking down a path where no one else is.
この世界は 群れていても 始まらない
Even if this world flocks together, nothing begins.
Yesでいいのか? サイレントマジョリティー
Is a 'Yes' okay? Silent Majority
もう三曲ね、ちゃんとね、
That's three songs now, properly,
曲も歌ったからね、しっかりね。
we sang the songs properly too.
この面子だとなんか安心感ある。
With this lineup, somehow there's a sense of security.
大丈夫、大丈夫、大丈夫かな?
It's okay, it's okay, is it okay?
よしよし、オッケー。
Alright, alright, okay.
元気いっぱい！いえーい！
Full of energy! Yay!
はい、というわけで、お聞きいただきましたのは、最初ね、ルナ姫とメルちゃん。
Yes, so what you just heard, first, Princess Luna and Mel-chan.
みおしと、えっと、おめおしゃとのフロス... フロス？
And Mio-shii, and, um, Omeosha's Flos... Flos?
そしてスバルのサイレントマジョリティーでしたー！
And Subaru's 'Silent Majority'!
この4曲、この4人たちはなんで選んだの?
Why did you choose these four people for these four songs?
きっとね、裏テーマは、低気圧ということで。
I'm sure the hidden theme was low atmospheric pressure.
やはり、低気圧はバラ... 低気圧はやっぱり低い気圧というか、バラ...
After all, low pressure is bara... Low pressure is after all low pressure, bara...
そういうイメージから選んで、なんか「これおしゃれだな」「おしゃれに歌いたいな」っていうところからね。
We chose it from that image, like 'This is stylish', 'I want to sing it stylishly'.
親戚のおじさん！
An uncle from the relatives!
おばあちゃんに
To a grandma
でもスバルちゃんが本当によかったんだよね。
But Subaru-chan was really great.
違うよ！おばさんにしてるんじゃなくて、ポルカと歌えて楽しかったよ。
No! Not making her an old lady, it was fun singing with Polka.
ありがとうございます！え、ルナ初めてバラード歌ったの！
Thank you! Eh, it's my first time singing a ballad, Luna!
ね、なんか、めっちゃ上手だったでしょ！
Right, you know, she was so good!
ちょっとドキドキしたのよ、バラード歌うの。
I was a bit nervous singing a ballad.
で も素敵だったよ！
But it was wonderful!
めっちゃ嬉しい！コメントとかも、あ、アシダもよろしく...
Super happy! Comments too, ah, Ashida too...
あ、足立も、よろしくお願いいたします！引き続き...
Ah, Adachi too, thank you very much! Continuing...
なんか、ちょっと頭痛いかもしれないな、なんか。
I feel like my head might hurt a little bit.
うそ、急にじゃんね。急にはやめてよ。
No way, so suddenly. Don't stop so suddenly.
ちょっと…
Wait...
水は盛り上げないよ、釣りはね
We're not hyping up water or fishing, right?
ちょっと今日ね
Today, um...
今日、なんかちょっと低気圧、低気圧じゃない？
Today, isn't it like... low pressure? Low pressure?
あ、確かにそうだった！今日低気圧気味なんだけど！
Ah, that's right! Today I feel a bit low pressure!
低気圧って…マジ？
Low pressure... seriously?
あ、もしかして…
Ah, could it be...
ちょっと待って決めても、ポルカさん、一応、ま、生誕祭だから、
Wait a minute, Polka-san, since it's your birthday event,
いつもはね、ちょっと休んでほしいんだけど、もうちょっと頑張って
usually I'd want you to rest, but please work a bit harder
あのほら、あのほらあれ、ホロメンからさ、ビデオレター今日もらってるでしょ？
You know, from holomembers, you got video letters today, right?
それはね、楽しみだね！
That's something to look forward to!
誰、誰、誰が来るの？誰が来るの？
Who, who, who is coming? Who is coming?
ちょっと待ってね
Hold on a second.
ビデオレターは？どうした？ビデオレター
What about the video letter? What happened? The video letter.
ビデオレター…皆さんいらっしゃったけど、低気圧に負けてビデオレターが1個も来てない、そうです！
Video letter... everyone's here, but not a single video letter arrived due to low pressure!
です！
That's right!
えー、低気圧バラエティ！低気圧敗北部！
Uh, Low Pressure Variety! Low Pressure Defeat Division!
はーい、みんな集まってねー！集まってねー！
Hiii, everyone gather around! Gather around!
はじまるよー！はじまるよー！始まってるよもう！
It's starting! It's starting! It's already started!
今日もね、早速始めていくよ、さっそく。なんなんだ？
Today too, we'll get right into it. What is this?
低気圧の、低気圧部の活動だからね、ずっと。
Because it's the activities of the low pressure club, always.
いや、そうだなあ、なんか…低気圧、なるほどなあ…
Yeah, that's right, like... low pressure, I see...
やばいよね、活動していきたいんだけどさあ、なんかこう、なんか…熱くなってきちゃったなあ…
It's dangerous, I want to do activities, but somehow... I'm getting hot...
え、頭痛くなくない、なんか？ちょっと…なんか…ちょっと痛いかも知れないな…
Eh, doesn't your head hurt a bit? Maybe it hurts a little...
確かに痛いかもしれないな！まあみんなとりあえず落ち着いてね。
It might really hurt! Well everyone calm down for now.
我が低気圧敗北部わ、低気圧弱々どもの集いし部。
Our Low Pressure Defeat Club is a gathering of weaklings against low pressure.
今日も低気圧に日々ね、負けながら、いつか勝てるその日を、その日ね、夢見て、低気圧の研究を欠かさない。
Every day losing to low pressure, dreaming of the day we can finally win, we never neglect our research on low pressure.
だがしかし、この中に一人、低気圧に強い人がい、いるらしい、ね。
But however, among us, there seems to be one person who is strong against low pressure.
いるらしい、うん。はい！というわけでね、はい、じゃあ今日はまずね、低気圧について…
Apparently so, yeah. Right! And so, yeah, today first, about low pressure...
あー、考えていくよ、考えるか今日も。じゃあ早速さ、
ah, we'll think about it, thinking about it today too. Then right away,
え、問題紹介、問題！問題、問題するよ。第1問！はい！
uh, introducing questions, a question! Question, we'll do questions. Question 1! Yes!
低気圧になると体に起きる現象は？答えよ！はい！
What phenomenon occurs in the body when atmospheric pressure is low? Answer! Yes!
現象！現象…君たちもなんか、早く…早打ちだって、早…
Phenomenon! Phenomenon... you guys also like, quickly... it's fast typing, fas...
早打ち、早い、早い、なんだっていいけど、えじゃあ、えじゃあすぐスバルなんか、スバルのフリップここに出すよ。
Fast typing, fast, fast, anything is fine, uh then, uh then Subaru, let's put Subaru's flip here.
え、ちょ、やめてよ！まだ書いてないよ！お、お、お、なんか書いてるけど…
Eh, wait, stop it! I haven't written it yet! O, o, o, writing something...
待って、待って、ねえ！なんか…
wait, wait, hey! Something...
何が違うの？何が違うの？
What's different? What's different?
何が違う？何が違う？
何が違う？やばえ、やばいね。
What's different? It's bad, it's terrible.
やべえのらしゅば。で、要は…何だろ、低気圧になって…
Terrible No La Shuba. And, the point is... I wonder what, low pressure becomes...
問題しかなくて、あの、部活だぞ！これさ、会話するやつじゃないんだよ。
There are only problems, it's club activities! This isn't something where you converse.
あれは要は、あのなんか屈強な何かで、なんか倒すんでしょ？
That is basically, defeating something with some sturdy something, right?
え、うんうん、低気圧！
Eh, yup yup, low pressure!
みおさんのフリップ。何これ？え、なんか…え、ちょっと、あ、わかる、わかる？
Mio-san's flip. What is this? Eh, like... eh, wait, ah, do you get it, do you get it?
ぶち切れちゃってるじゃん！
You're totally snapping!
要は低気圧だから、だるい、だるい、だるい、だるい、だるい…ってなるんだよ。
The point is because of low pressure, sluggish, sluggish, sluggish... that's how it is.
みおしゃして…みおしゃ、みおしゃ…めおしゃステップ。
Mio-sha... Mio-sha, Mio-sha... Meo-sha step.
どうやってやるのみおしゃステップって、こんな感じ？なんかちょっと違うな、なんかちょっと違うぞ。
How do you do the Mio-sha step, like this? It feels a bit different, a bit different.
違うよポルポル、こうだよ！なんですかそれ、スバルが近いかな？スバル本当にお前低気圧に敗北してんのか？
That's wrong Polpol, it's like this! What is that, is Subaru closer? Subaru, are you really defeated by low pressure?
あったかいって、やっぱ。簡単だったよ、ちゃんと。じゃあちょっと、そうだな、ひめにちゃんにちゃんと模範解答を書いてもらって…
It's warm, after all. It was easy, properly. Well then, Hime-ni-chan, please write a proper model answer...
低気圧になると起こる現象、これは？
The phenomenon that occurs when atmospheric pressure drops, what is this?
どうだ？姫。
"How is it, Luna?"
うんな…おおっ！頭痛、眠い、だるい…
"Um... Oh...! Headache, sleepy, sluggish..."
わかるー！わかるーなのだ！
"I know, right! Totally know!"
ずつー、ねむい、だるい、しぬ、しぬ、しぬ
"Hea-dache, sleepy, sluggish, dying, dying, dying"
死ぬ？
"Dying?"
もう大変じゃん！そんな昨日わ！
"That's awful! Yesterday was like that!"
そんなことにまでなるの？
"It gets to that point?"
やばくない？
"Isn't that crazy?"
やばすぎるよね、これ。
"It's way too crazy, this."
これ、気圧なら分かるよね。
"If it's barometric pressure, you get it, right?"
分かるよー。
"I get it."
あの、起き上がれない。
"Like, you can't get up."
なんんならさっきもポルカ始まるまでもうそこの部活動始まるぎりぎりまでさーもう寝てたもん。
"In fact, right up until the club activities started just now, I was sleeping right over there."
天気の子きてる！きてるよ、これ。
"The weather's spirit is here! It's here!"
ほら気圧席でさ、もう気圧の椅子があるのにここでずっと寝てたんだもん。寝てたね。
"Look, even though there's a pressure seat, you were sleeping right here the whole time. You were sleeping."
地獄。
"Hell."
だるさがきてるねー。
"The sluggishness is setting in."
じゃあさ、みおしゃももう普通にさっきのだるいがいいの？正解。
"So, Mio-sha, is your 'sluggish' from earlier the correct answer?"
あれ？あれは正解なの？みおしゃの。みおしゃの中の正解はなんかあのえっえっえっえっえっ
"Wait? Is that the correct answer? Mio-sha's. What's the correct answer for Mio-sha... um, um, um, um..."
永眠…ってコト?!
"Eternal sleep... you mean?!"
永眠ってこと？さっきのさっきの
"Eternal sleep? Just a second ago..."
もう…もう…もう…永眠ってこと？やったー！にひっぱられ…にひっぱられ…
"Already... already... already... eternal sleep? Yay! Dragged into... dragged into..."
え、どういうこと？
"Wh-what do you mean?"
死ぬって言ったからね。
"Because you said 'dying'."
そうそうそう、そういうこと。
"Right, right, exactly."
唯一ふざけられる、みおしゃがふざけられる場所がここってことなの？
"So this is the only place where Mio-sha can goof off?"
じゃあみおしゃさ、もうお手本見せてよ低気圧の国民として。おなかがへる！！！
"Then Mio-sha, show us an example as a low-pressure citizen! 'I'm starving!'"
新しく書き直しただろお前！その鳥みたいな。いややっぱりそのだるいだるいだるいだるいを引きずってるの、これは。
"You rewrote it, didn't you! That bird-like thing. No, you're still dragging 'sluggish, sluggish, sluggish', aren't you, this is!"
え、ちょっと気圧の木もっかい見ていい？
"Wait, can I look at the pressure tree again?"
え？気圧の木何語や。おなかがへる！！！
"Eh? What language is the pressure tree? 'I'm starving!'"
あ、でも書き直してるよ。だいたいあってんじゃん。だいたいあってんじゃん。一応あってんみたいなとかある。あ、ちゃんと書き直してる。だるいがたりは辞めてくださいよ。おなかがへる。
"Ah, but you rewrote it. It's mostly right. It's mostly right. It's kind of close, right? Ah, you rewrote it properly. Please stop with 'sluggish is lacking'. 'I'm starving'."
えでもそれより気になるのはおなかが減りますか低気圧で。おなかが減ります。低気圧じゃないときも減ります。
"Eh, but what I'm more curious about is, do you get hungry from low pressure? I get hungry. I get hungry even when it's not low pressure."
だって眠気よりは可能性はあるでしょ、絶対！
"I mean, there's definitely a higher chance of that than sleepiness!"
どういうこと？でもだるいだるいだるいだるいって書いてるよ、みおしゃは。
"What do you mean? But Mio-sha wrote 'sluggish, sluggish, sluggish, sluggish'."
だるいだるいだるい元気だろ！おかしいだろ！
"Sluggish, sluggish, sluggish, you have energy! That's weird!"
なるほどね。ということで、はい。
"I see. And so, yes."
まあみんなもお分かりのとおりね、もしとは低気圧よくなくないすか？
"Well, as you all know, aren't low pressures not very good?"
なんだってー？
"What was that?!"
低気圧。もっとこいよ！
"Low pressure. Bring it on more!"
ほらー！もっと来いやー！大本通りのセリフ読んだ。大本通りのセリフ読んだ。
"Look! Bring it on! You read the script line just like that. You read the script line."
元気！元気のなーいーやーつー！低気圧がさ、って！
"Energy! An unenergetic person! Saying low pressure is...!"
低気圧を感じたことがあまりない。え？マジ？
"I haven't felt low pressure much before. Eh? Really?"
でもさっきさ、眠いかも知れない。これは低気圧ってこと？って言ってたよ。
"But earlier you said, 'I might be sleepy. Does this mean it's low pressure?'"
言ったらみおしゃが、スパルご飯食べたからそれ、血圧、血糖値
"When I said that, Mio-sha said she ate Suparu rice, so that's blood pressure, blood sugar level..."
原因がなんか違うみたいですね。
"The cause seems to be a bit different."
はいはいはいはい。じゃあね、ポルカもでもほぼほぼみなさんが書いたように、あ、頭痛、頭痛？あ、頭痛痛い？あ、眠気？うん、あー
"Right, right, right. Well then, Polka also, pretty much just like what everyone wrote—uh, headache, headache? Ah, headache hurts? Ah, sleepiness? Yeah, uh—"
だるい、起き上がれない、やる気ない、もう無理。
"Sluggish, can't get up, unmotivated, no way."
もうなんか、もうなんか、何もやりたくない、減っていきたい、減っていきたい。やる気は気のせいなんじゃないの？
"Already like, already like, don't want to do anything, want to decrease, want to decrease. Isn't motivation just all in your head?"
やる気のせい？えー！これは低気圧の根性。
"Motivation's fault? Eh?! This is low-pressure grit."
そうやってさ、すぐさ、まあレジャーとかの中身しゃあないけどさ、根性論、根性論。
"You always immediately—well, leisure stuff can't be helped, but it's all about grit and willpower."
ルナさん、見て！未だにプロ意識高いから、フリップでもこんなこと書いてるよ。
"Luna-san, look! Her professional awareness is still so high, she's writing stuff like this even on her flipbook."
すごいよ、このプロ意識。ねむいって。
"It's amazing, this professional awareness. 'Sleepy', it says."
低気圧に対するプロ意識の高さがこれ。そういうこと！ねむい！
"This is the height of professional awareness towards low pressure. Exactly! Sleepy!"
なるほどね。よし、それ帰って終わるで。ねむい、ねむい、ねむい、ねむい、ねむい、ねむい。
"I see. All right, let's wrap it up with that. Sleepy, sleepy, sleepy, sleepy, sleepy, sleepy."
ちなみに、えっと、今日の夜から、んと、明日、明日あたりはね、ポルカも来てるんだけど、みおしゃは明日っぽいね。
"By the way, uh, starting tonight, um, tomorrow, around tomorrow right, Polka has it too, but Mio-sha seems to be tomorrow."
うちもまだ来てない。何が来てんの？低気圧が。
"Mine hasn't come yet either. What's coming? Low pressure."
天気の子？どういうこと？ねえ、今から来るよ。
"Weathering With You? What do you mean? Hey, it's coming starting now."
気圧が、来るよ！
"The barometric pressure is coming!"
来すぎでしょ、そんな天気の子！なんて、なんて、その天気の子！
"That's way too much, Weathering With You! What, what is that Weathering With You!"
いろんな意見出てますけれど、まだ欲しいですか？
"Various opinions are being shared, but do you still want more?"
いや、まだ欲しくはない。まだ求めてるの？
"No, I don't want any more. Are you still asking for it?"
いやいや、みおしゃがなんかまたね、なんかだるいだるいだるいだるいって言ってさ、LINEスタンプみたいなのを発売しようとしてるから
"No no, Mio-sha is like, again, saying 'sluggish sluggish sluggish sluggish' and trying to release LINE stamps or something"
それ欲しい！
"I want that!"
なんだこれ、新しいの何これ？低気圧。ねちゃったわ。
"What is this, what's this new one? Low pressure. I fell asleep."
みおしゃ、本当に面白すぎるよこれ。いろんな
"Mio-sha, this is really too funny. Various..."
いろんな、いろんな意見が出ましたが、
Various, various opinions were raised, but
ああ、でも、まあ私、部長です。
Well, anyway, I'm the club president.
まあ、まあ、まあ、まあ、まあ。
Well, well, well, well, well.
低気圧のこと分からない。
I don't know anything about low pressure.
え?
Eh?
え?どういうこと?低気圧、部長なのに?
Eh? What do you mean? You're the president, yet you don't know?
部長なのにわかんないんですか?
You're the president and you don't know?
いや、言い訳に使ってるわけでもないんだけど、わかんないんだよ。
No, it's not like I'm using it as an excuse, but I just don't get it.
わかんない、わかんないんだよ、これがいったい。
I don't get it, I just don't get what this is at all.
なぜこんなに頭が痛くて眠いのかがわからない。
I don't know why my head hurts so much and why I'm so sleepy.
わかんないくせにさっきまで頭が痛ててたのかよ、こいつ。
Even though you don't get it, you were just complaining about a headache!
うるせえ!
Shut up!
うざい!うざい!うざい!うざい!ひどいよお!
Annoying! Annoying! Annoying! Annoying! That's awful!
部長としてポルカ情けないよ。
As president, Polka, that's pathetic.
もうこの部も解体だよ。
This club is getting dismantled!
えーー!それは困るでしょ!
Ehh! But that's a problem!
だって今日はせっかく集まったばっかだしね。
I mean, we just gathered today after all.
そうなんだよ!せっかく集まったばっかだし!
That's right! We just got together!
本日はなんと特別ゲストにお越しいただいております!
And today, we have a very special guest joining us!
おお!
Oh!
誰々?誰々?
Who? Who?
誰々?誰々?誰々?山岸さん?
Who? Who? Yamagishi-san?
ウェザーニュースキャスターの山岸愛梨です!よろしくお願いします!
I'm Airi Yamagishi, Weathernews caster! Nice to meet you!
初めまして!よろしくお願いします!
Nice to meet you! Looking forward to it!
ウェザーニュースキャスターの山岸愛梨と申します。ポルカさん、お誕生日おめでとうございます!
I'm Airi Yamagishi, Weathernews caster. Polka-san, happy birthday!
おめでとう!
Happy birthday!
ちょっと、ちょっと、ちょっと、おめでとうございます、ありがとうございます!
Wait, wait, wait, happy birthday, thank you so much!
誕生日は、誕生日だった!
It was my birthday! It is my birthday!
忘れられてて、やってもらいましたけど、低気圧で忘れ…いやね、そう。低気圧なのとちゃんと…
I was forgotten and had you do it, but forgotten due to low pressure... Well, yeah. Low pressure and properly...
ねえ、もう本当すごいんだよ、この山岸さんが来てくれたこと、皆さんと一緒に…
Hey, it's really amazing that Yamagishi-san came here, together with everyone...
ポルカちゃんとも!
And with Polka-chan!
いやだって、すごい…
I mean, it's amazing...
バシッと決めたいわけだもんね。
You want to pull it off sharply, right?
ポルカのサーカスにまで来てくれるとか。
Like coming all the way to Polka's circus.
おー!やばすぎだろ。
Oh! That's way too crazy.
やばすぎだな。そう。
Way too crazy. Yeah.
で、気象予報士としても、ウェザーニュースキャスターとしても超大活躍してる、天才でめっさ美人のゲストさんです。
And as a weather forecaster and Weathernews caster, she's a super successful, genius, and super beautiful guest!
べっぴん!
A stunner!
おおー!
Ooh!
すごい!すごーい!
Amazing! Ama-zing!
はい!
Yes!
はい!すごい!すごい!
Yes! Amazing! Amazing!
どうしたらいいかわかんない。
I don't know what to do.
どうしたらいいかわかんない、ポルカのテンションが高すぎ。
You don't know what to do, Polka's tension is way too high.
いや、ちょっとね、おだてがられると困っちゃいますもんね。
Well, you know, it gets awkward when you flatter me like that.
そうですね。
That's right.
じゃあ、ちょっと低気圧になってくわ。ふー。
Well then, I'll go into low pressure mode. Whew.
え、どういうこと?やめて、やめて、MCのお前が低気圧になってどうすんだよ。
Eh, what do you mean? Stop it, what are you doing as the MC turning low pressure?
わかんない、わかんない、メカニズムが分かんないって言ってて。
She said she doesn't get the mechanism.
ねえ、メカニズムが分かんないって言ってて。
Hey, she said she doesn't get the mechanism.
山岸さんのさ、ねえ、意思の疎通が難しいっていうか。
Yamagishi-san, well, communication is kind of difficult.
いやいや、めんどくせえな、こいつ。
No no, she's such a pain.
来てくれたんだよ!
She came here!
やばい、私かしいね。
Oh dear, I'm so embarrassing.
そう。はい、低気圧。
Yeah. Right, low pressure.
と、我らの関係について聞きたいんです、ぜひ。
And we'd love to hear about our relationship.
関係について?
About the relationship?
我々、いや、低気圧のね、敗北部がいつか低気圧に勝てるようなことをいろいろ教えていただきたいです!
We—well, we'd like you to teach us how the defeatist low-pressure club can eventually triumph over low pressure!
おお!
Ooh!
おおー!
はい、任せてください!
Yes, leave it to me!
えー、勝てるかなー?
Ehh, can we win?
頑張りましょう!
Let's do our best!
勝てるのかな?
Can we win?
いやー、勝ちたい!
Man, I want to win!
まず、そもそもポルカがさっき部長やめようかなって言ってたように、その低気圧ってどういう状態なの?
First of all, like Polka said earlier about quitting as president, what kind of state is low pressure anyway?
お、でも知りたい!低気圧って何ねえ。元々の部分ね。
Oh, but I want to know! What is low pressure anyway. The original part.
ねえ、天気予報でよく登場するので、皆さん聞いたことはあると思いますけれども。
Well, since it frequently appears in weather forecasts, I think everyone has heard of it.
周囲に比べて気圧の低いところを低気圧と言います。
Areas where atmospheric pressure is lower than the surrounding area are called low pressure.
おおー!
Ooh!
周囲との差によって決まるので、何ヘクトパスカル以下が低気圧みたいなものはないんですよ。
It's determined by the difference with the surroundings, so there's no rule like "below X hectopascals is low pressure."
へえー!
I see!
で、低気圧がやってくると、気圧が下がりますよね。
And when a low-pressure system approaches, the atmospheric pressure drops.
で、この気圧の変化によって引き起こされる不調のことを天気痛って言うんですよ。
And the physical discomfort caused by this change in pressure is called weather sickness.
ええー!
Ehhh!
皆さん天気痛です。
Everyone has weather sickness.
じゃあ低気圧病じゃなくて天気痛っていうんですか?
So instead of low-pressure disease, it's called weather sickness?
天気痛っていうんですよ。天気痛、そうなんだ。
It's called weather sickness. Weather sickness, is that right.
気圧とか湿度とか気温の変化によって引き起こされることがあって、頭が痛くなったりとか、痛い。関節が痛くなったり、いろいろ症状があります。
It can be triggered by changes in pressure, humidity, or temperature, causing headaches, joint pain, and various other symptoms.
本日だ!
That's today!
本日までなんだって!
Even until today!
だから季節の変わり目って体調崩すんですか?
Is that why people's health breaks down at the change of seasons?
そうです、そうです。季節の変わり目は気温の変化も大きいですし。強いな。そうですね、でもよく言うよね、なんか。
That's right, that's right. The change of seasons has big temperature changes too. So strong. That's right, but people often say that.
確かにな。そうなんだ。
True. That's true.
なんかこう線を越えたらもうやばいのかなとかさ、そのヘクトパスカルのそのなのかなあって思ってただけで、別に上下のこういう乱高下じゃないけど、上にいったり下にいったり軽っていう、なんかそういう感じなんすかね?
I just wondered if crossing a certain line means it's dangerous, or if it's about those hectopascals, but is it more about those ups and downs, going up and down lightly, something like that?
あ、そうですね。急激な変化で体調に影響が出ることがあるので、
Ah, that's right. Rapid changes can affect your health,
あの、きっと飛行機に乗って上に行ったりする時の気圧の変化みたいなことですよね、きっとね。
so it's probably like the change in pressure when you get on an airplane and go up, right?
あ、て、
Ah, te,
それとは違うんです。天気痛が、症状が出る方は、そういう気圧の変化もあまり得意じゃない方が多いと思います。
that's different. People who suffer from weather sickness probably aren't very good with those pressure changes either.
エレベーターのさ、ぐーって上にいくと、耳が痛いよー、あーってなるよね。
Like when an elevator goes way up, your ears hurt, ahh, like that.
そっか。
I see.
それだ、それだ。これなのかな?それだ、たぶん。
That's it, that's it. Is this it? That's probably it.
それも、ネット…ね？
Well, also... the internet, right?
笑いじゃないよ、会長っ！
It's no laughing matter, Chairman!
笑いじゃないかもしれないけどさ！
It might not be, but still!
気圧の変動がね、体へ影響してるんですよね。
Pressure fluctuations really do affect the body.
そうですね。
That's right.
はい、聞きたいことがあります。
Right, I have something I want to ask.
はい、スバルさんどうしました？
Yes, Subaru-san, what is it?
はい！なんでスバルは低気圧効かないんですか？
Yes! Why doesn't low pressure affect Subaru?
あ、なんでよ！
Hey, why's that?!
え、なんだろ、なんでさ、効く人間と効かない人間がいてさ。
Yeah, why is it that some people are affected and others aren't?
確かにね。
True, huh.
え、そう、だから不思議なんだよ、なんか気圧って目に見えないから、本当に、なんか、ど、痛いの？みたいなさ。
Yeah, so it's mysterious, since atmospheric pressure is invisible, like, does it actually hurt? Or what?
痛いの？痛いのどうなのよ！
Does it hurt? How does it hurt?!
なんかさ、視聴者さんでもさ、「え、何言ってんのポルカ？」みたいな人いるじゃん、本当に。いや、もうそっち側の人間だよスバルは。
Even among viewers, some are like, "Huh, what is Polka saying?" Seriously. I mean, Subaru is definitely on that side.
いや、今みたいなさ、そ、でも弱い人の特徴。
Wait, like right now, but the characteristics of sensitive people...
そう、なんでなる人はなっちゃうんですか？
Right, why do certain people end up getting it?
あの、気圧の変化をこう感じるようなセンサーのようなものが耳の奥にある内耳って言われてるんですけれど、
Um, there's something like a sensor deep inside the ear that feels changes in atmospheric pressure, called the inner ear.
そうなんですよ。この変化が大きいと、この内耳がまあ影響しまして、自律神経のバランスが崩れてしまうんですよね。
That's right. When this change is large, the inner ear is affected, and the balance of the autonomic nervous system gets disrupted.
自律神経、それにも？そう、影響してしまうので、
The autonomic nervous system, that too? Right, it affects that, so
内耳が敏感な方は結構影響しやすいと思うので、
people with sensitive inner ears are probably quite susceptible to it.
もしかするとスバルさんは内耳が鈍感なのかも。
So maybe Subaru-san's inner ear is just insensitive.
待って！内耳が鈍感？え、それって普段大声で喋ってることと関係ありますか？
Wait! An insensitive inner ear? Does that have anything to do with talking loudly all the time?!
どうでしょうね？みんな結構大きな声で喋ってると思うんですけど。
Who knows? I think everyone speaks pretty loudly.
あ、確かに！確かに！
Ah, true! True!
な、内耳が強いんだって！やった！
M-My inner ear is strong! Yay!
でもね、耳が悪いわけじゃないから、よく聞こえるの、逆にいろんな声が。え？そういう、耳は悪い方だろ、多分スバルは。
But you know, it's not that your ears are bad, you actually hear various voices better, inversely. Huh? Your ears are probably on the worse side, Subaru.
いや、だから結局自律神経ってことですよね。なんかその、内耳から入って、で、その影響で自律神経を崩しやすい人と崩しにくい人で差が出て るってことですかね？
No, so in the end, it's about the autonomic nervous system, right? Like, it enters from the inner ear, and because of that effect, there's a difference between people whose autonomic nervous system gets easily disrupted and those who don't?
そうなんです。自律神経が乱れてくると、体調に影響が出ることがあるので、
That's right. When the autonomic nervous system gets disordered, it can affect your physical condition,
えー、そうなんですよ。
so... exactly.
乗り物酔いしやすい方はもしかすると天気痛も…
People who easily get motion sickness might also have weather pain...
え、乗り物酔いめっっちゃする！
Eh, I get *so* motion sick!
乗り物酔いめちゃする。あれ？
I get super motion sick. Huh?
あれ？あれ？あれ、なんでだ？乗り物酔い…
Huh? Huh? Huh, why is that? Motion sickness...
乗り物酔いしません。
I don't get motion sick.
え、なんで？え？ゲームも酔いません。
Eh, why? Eh? I don't get motion sick from games either.
え！？ゲーム酔うだけどめっっちゃする！めっっちゃ酔うぐらいよ！
Eh?! I get *so* motion sick from games! Like, super motion sick!
椅子グルグル回っても大丈夫っす。えー！？
I'm totally fine spinning around in a chair. What?!
でも低気圧弱いです。
But low pressure is my weakness.
なんで！えー！？天気痛か。
Why?! Eh?! Weather pain, huh.
でも、みおしゃは乗り物酔いだから、実際するんだよね、乗り物酔い。
But Miosha gets motion sick, so she actually does get motion sick.
するね、画面酔いもするし。同じだー。
Yeah, and screen sick too. Same here.
えー。
Ehh.
ちょっとね、ルーナといっしょっぽいなうちは。
I guess I'm kind of similar to Luna.
そうな。はい！はい！
Is that so. Yes! Yes!
スバルさん、これ痛い人とかはどうやったら直せるんですか？
Subaru-san, for people who experience this pain, how can they fix it?
すごい、優しい。聞いてくれるのね、痛くないのに聞いてくれるなんて。
How kind. Asking about it even though it doesn't affect you.
ま、対策は色々あるんですけれど、まずは規則正しい生活を心がける。
Well, there are various countermeasures, but first is trying to keep a regular lifestyle.
やべえ、ここ人たち多分全員ヴァンパイアみたいな生活してっぞ！
Yikes, everyone here probably lives like vampires!
規則正しい生活…！
A regular lifestyle...!
ま、早寝早起きとか。
Well, sleeping early and waking up early, etc.
はい、あとは、あとはちゃんと一日三食ご飯を食べる。
Right, and also eating three meals a day properly.
あー！食べてる？みんな？
Ah! Are you eating? Everyone?
食べてる！食べてる、食べてる！
Eating! Eating, eating!
食べてるからなー。あ、じゃあそういうこと？やば。
Because we eat. Ah, so that's it? Yikes.
守れてません…！守れてないかも。
We aren't protecting it... We might not be protecting it.
日光は浴びたりとかしないといけないのか、じゃあやっぱり。
So we need to get sunlight and stuff, huh.
あ、日光も浴びたほうがいいですね。浴びてる？浴びてる、外よく出る。
Ah, it's better to get sunlight too. Are you getting it? I am, I go outside a lot.
カーテン締めっぱだろ？
You keep your curtains closed all the time, right?
え、でもダンスとかでちょっとうるさいよ、その、うるさいだろ？ステイステイステイステイステイ！夜ギシしたの5000で何をしてるんだ？
Well, but for dancing and stuff, it's a bit noisy, right? Stay, stay, stay, stay, stay! What are you doing with 5000 creaks at night?!
ステイステイステイだぞ、争ってしまってはいないね。
It's stay, stay, stay, we shouldn't be fighting, right?
なんか、ポルカは漢方もしめ、勧められたんです、五苓散とか。
Somehow, Polka was recommended Kampo medicine too, like Goreisan.
あーいうの飲んでたら効くんですかね、いつか？
If you take stuff like that, does it work eventually?
そうですね、漢方も結構天気痛の緩和が期待できるって言われてるので、お医者さんと相談しながら。
That's right, Kampo is said to be expected to help alleviate weather pain, so while consulting with a doctor...
相談しながらね。
Consulting with them, yeah.
あ、あの、あとわちはホロライブJPですけど、ENのヤン、IDもいて、そのイングリッシュやインドネシアとかも普通に低気圧がうーぷすってなるんですかね？
Ah, um, also, our group is Hololive JP, but there's also EN and ID, and do English or Indonesian members also just go "oops" when low pressure hits?
お、えっと、日本以外で、そうですね。
Oh, um, outside of Japan, that's right.
地域によってね、どうなるの？
Depending on the region, how does it affect them?
そうですね、あの、あんまりまだ天気痛って解明されてない部分もあったりするので、
That's right, um, weather pain hasn't been fully elucidated in some parts yet,
解明されてない？
hasn't been elucidated?
の多くでどれくらいみんながこう困っててっていうのはまだわかっていない部分もあるんですけれども
There are still parts we don't fully understand about how much everyone struggles with this,
ま基本的にはこう日本って多分天気痛引き起こされやすい条件がいろいろ整ってるんですよね
but basically, Japan has various conditions that easily trigger weather-related pain.
湿気がそうはっきりしてたりとか台風がやってきたり
Like clear humidity or typhoons approaching.
なんか似たように結構こう湿気があって気温の変化が大きくてっていうところは同じように影響が出て困ってる方もいるんじゃないかなと思うんですよね
So I think there are people who similarly suffer from the effects of humidity and large temperature changes.
もし超悩んでたら海外に進めばもしかしたら克服できるとかそういう
If you're super troubled by it, maybe moving abroad... That's what Polka has always thought.
天気痛するかもよ
You might get weather pain!
あとは逆にずっと何にもなんか知らなかった人とかが日本に来て超長期滞在してあれ？頭が痛いずっと頭が痛いとかになったりするのかなっていうのもすごい謎だし
On the other hand, what's also a mystery is if people who didn't know anything about it come to Japan for a long stay and start getting constant headaches.
確かにね。どうなんだろう。
True. I wonder about that.
で山根さんはどうなんすか？やっぱ天気気圧って結構来ます？今日とか。
And Yamane-san, how about you? Do you get affected by barometric pressure? Like today?
私もう全く感じないんですよ。
I don't feel it at all.
ええ！？
What?!
感じないんです！
I don't feel it at all!
なんか喜んでんだよ。
Look how happy she is.
同じスバルちゃんと一緒で
Just like Subaru-chan!
よかった！
Yay!
山根さんもあれですか、あの結構外に結構行かれるタイプですか？
Yamane-san, are you the type who goes outside a lot?
私はもう超インドアです。
I'm super indoors.
あれ？あれ？
Huh? Huh?
全く出かけない。何にも気ををつけてるんですか？
I barely go out. What do you even watch out for?
何にも気をつけてないですね。寝るのも遅いし起きるのも遅いし
I don't watch out for anything. Sleeping late, waking up late...
ええ！なんで！？
Huh?! Why?!
なんでしょうかね？
I wonder why?
なんただろう、お母さんやお父さんがじゃあすごいもともと低気圧に強い
Maybe your mom or dad were originally strong against low pressure?
え、でもじゃあマジでやっぱ生まれたときに決まんのかな？
Wait, so is it really decided when you're born?
え、でも変わらないの？その天気
Wait, doesn't it change? Weather-related...
それはちょっと、Lamyちゃん。
That's a bit, Lamy-chan.
でも、なんかその苦手な人でも生活習慣を改善することによってましになる可能性があるってことですよね。
But, it means even if you're not good with it, improving lifestyle habits can make it better.
そうですね。規則正しい生活を心がけたりとか、あとマッサージもありますよ。
That's right. Keeping regular habits, and there are massages too.
マッサージ？
Massages?
はい。くるくる耳マッサージっていうのがある。
Yes. There's the "spin-spin ear massage."
え、教えてほしいです。
Please teach us.
くるくるするんですよ。耳の血流を良くするために、耳をですね、引っ張りながら。上下左右に5秒ずつ引っ張るといい。
To improve blood circulation in the ears, you pull them up, down, left, right for 5 seconds each.
おお～、引っ張る。5秒ずつね。
Ooh, pulling. 5 seconds each.
いやこれ大変だよ。がんばってつまんでる。
Man, this is tough. Pinching hard.
温かくなってくる。
It gets warm.
で、あと後ろに5回回す。頑張れ、頑張れ。
And then rotate backwards 5 times. Hang in there, hang in there.
なんか気持ちいいような。
It feels kind of good.
聞いてるこれ？
Is this working?
わかんないなあ。すぐ終わる。
I don't know. It ends quickly.
あと折りたたむ。折りたたむ？耳たぶじゃ大変だよ。
And fold them. Fold them? Earlobe folding is tough.
耳みんな、がんばってがんばって。私はでも耳触られるの気持ちいいタイプだから。なるほどね。
Everyone's ears, hang in there. But I'm the type who likes having my ears touched. I see.
でも山根さんも思いませんか？仕事のスイッチ入っちゃうとこれやっても関係なくないですか？
But Yamane-san, don't you think? Once work mode switches on, does doing this even matter?
え、どういうこと？え、家でやるとようやくこうスイッチが入るのか
Eh, what do you mean? Eh, do you finally switch on when you do it at home?
リラックスできるみたいにできると、仕事中にこれやっても
If you can relax like that, doing this during work...
確かに、今ちょっと違うかもしれないですね。
True, it might be a bit different right now.
そうっすよね！仕事中にやるといいって話です。
That's right! Doing it during work is good.
マジです。
Seriously.
そう。そういうことですよ、皆さんだから。皆さんが今うーんってやってたらね、もしかするととみや、ポルカのためにみんな頑張ってるからかもしれないっすよ。
Exactly. That's what it is, everyone. So if you're going "hmm" right now, maybe everyone is working hard for Polka.
じゃあリラックスしている時にやるとより効果的ということですか？
So you mean it's more effective when you're relaxed?
絶対そうでしょう。
Definitely, right?
そうですね、あの基本的にはもう天気痛に悩まされて頭が痛いとか症状が出る前からやっておくといいらしいので
That's right. Basically, it's good to do it before symptoms like weather headaches start.
なるほど！出る前にやんなきゃ意味ないんだ。
I see! Doing it before it starts is the only point.
そう、朝昼晩毎日やっといたほうがいいらしい。
Right, you should apparently do it every morning, noon, and night.
ポルポル！
Polpol!
え、もうだめなの？
Eh, no good anymore?
でもちかにお頭痛とか聞く、なんかさ、頭痛はさ、頭痛がする前に飲むとかさ、天気痛のそのさ、ツールみたいなのを見ながら、あ、そろそろ来るから先に飲んでおこうみたいなのがあったりするんですけど
But certainly headaches... like, take medicine before a headache starts, or while looking at weather pain tools, "Ah, it's coming soon, let's take some first."
なんかやっぱり薬に頼りすぎるのも良くないですよね。
But relying too much on medicine isn't good either, right?
だから毎日もうやんなくちゃこれ。毎日やらなきゃだめよ。
So you gotta do it every day. You gotta do it every day.
じゃあ山根さんもやってね。私もやります。全然。
Then Yamane-san do it too. I'll do it too. Not a problem.
天気痛に効くコツを教えてくれたからね、山根さんは言うよ。
Since you taught us tips that work for weather pain, Yamane-san says.
え、そうだな。
Ah, that's right.
こっちじゃねえんだな、おい。
Not this side, hey!
終、山根さんどうですか？ここまで話しててこの人たちは楽しそうな人たちですか？
Shuu, Yamane-san, how is it? Talking up to here, are these people having fun?
すごい気が気じゃないです。質問って思いますがね。天気痛に果たしてそうですかね。
I'm super anxious. I think it's a question. Is weather pain really like that?
あ、そうですね。やっぱりこれだけのもうパワフルなみんななので、乗り切れると思います。
Ah, that's right. Since everyone is this powerful, I think we can push through.
本当ですか？
Really?
よかった！
Yay!
よかったよかった！
Good, good!
じゃあ今日でこの部活は解散だ！
Then starting today, this club is dissolved!
待ってくれ！もうすでに終わるらしいから。
Wait! Apparently it's already ending.
部活から低気圧を回復する部じゃなくて、低気圧敗北改善部にしようじゃ。
Instead of a club recovering from low pressure, let's make it the low-pressure defeat improvement club!
改善！
Improvement!
対策方法みたいな感じで
Like, through measures like that...
山岸さんにもたまに来てもらいたいからそういうのにして
I want Yamagishi-san to come sometimes too, so we made it something like that.
うんうんうん。え、でも来てもいいんですか?
Eh, is it okay if she comes?
えっ!?
Yeah!
いいの、面白い!
That's interesting!
テンション!
The tension!
来てくれよ。えっ、マジ?
Come on! Eh, seriously?
期待です、また。
I want you to come again!
やった!やった!
Yay! Yay!
山岸さん、あの、大丈夫ですか?
Yamagishi-san, um, are you okay?
後頭部に銃とか当てられてないですか?
You haven't had a gun pointed at your nape, right?
えっ?
Eh?
脅されてないですか?大丈夫ですか?
You haven't been forced, right? Are you okay?
脅されて...
Have you been forced?
脅されてないですよね?
You haven't been forced, right?
山岸さん普段からみんなの配信見てるので、
Yamagishi-san usually watches everyone's streams, so...
えっ!?
Eh?
めちゃくちゃ嬉しかったんですよ。
She said she was so, so happy!
本当に!
Really?
やったー!
Yay!
ありがとうございます!
Thank you so much!
いやっていうか、本当にありがとうございました。
Yeah, I mean, thank you so much!
頑張って!
Good luck!
頑張って、えっと...
Good luck, um...
低気圧を破滅、なんていうの?
Surviving low atmospheric pressure--
破滅、破滅か。
Ruination-- destruction!
破滅してきまーす!
We're gonna go destroy low pressure!
破滅?
Destruction!
バイバーイ!ありがとうございます!
Bye-bye! Thank you!
できすかな?
Have you had enough?
破滅!ありがとう!
Destruction! Thank you!
ありがとうございました!またねー!
Thank you so much! See you again!
破滅、破滅!
Destruction, destruction!
可愛い。
So cute.
今のが冗談かわかんなくて可愛かったね。
I couldn't tell when she was joking, it was so cute.
"可愛い"ってついちゃったね。
She just added "So cute!" out of nowhere.
可愛いね。
So cute.
よし、じゃあみんなこれで耳マッサージもできたことだし、出来た?
Alright, so everyone, we've successfully done ear massages, right?
できた?できたことだし!
Did you? It's done, right?
よっしゃ!
Alright!
明日に向かって、ゴールデンの明日に向かってね。
Heading towards tomorrow, let's head to the golden tomorrow!
ゴールデン!
Golden!
いきますよ!
Let's go!
あ、Qどうした?
What happened to Q?
この今日のヒストリーを忘れずに、
Don't forget today's history!
向かって、歌おう!
Let's head there! Let's sing!
あっちに行くぞ!
Let's go over there!
あっちどこ?
Where's over there?
あっち?あっち、あっちだよ!
Over there? Over there!
ゴールデンだ!
Golden!
あっち、あっち、あっち、あっち!
Over there, over there!
ヒストリー!
Wait, history!
あ、なんかあっちに出てきた。
Oh, something's coming out over there!
なんかあっち低気圧ある!低気圧ある!
Wait, there's low pressure! There's low pressure!
こっちだ、こっちこっち!こっちだ!
Over here, over here, over here!
なんで置いてくの?なんで置いてくの?
Why are you leaving me behind? Why are you leaving me behind?
なんで置いてくの!?
Why are you leaving me behind?!
さあ 始めよう
Now, let's begin.
収穫の時はきた やってきた
The time for harvest has come.
汗かいて前向いてやってきた
Sweating and facing forward, we've arrived.
やっていきましょう!
Let's go!
ザ・ゴールデン・ヒストリー!
The Golden History!
最後はポルカが突き抜ける!
Let's have Polka's climax!
さあ、行くぞ!ありがとう!
Let's go! Thank you!
それでは 最初 ポルカがツッコミます!
Now, let's start with Polka's comment!
試練に負けず 自然に負けず
We've come this far without losing to trials, naturally not losing,
「歌」にさえして夢みた
turning even "songs" into dreams.
実れば実るほど ヘイヘイヘイ
The more it bears fruit, hey, hey, hey!
分け合える稲穂 ヘイヘイホー
Rice ears we can share, hey, hey, ho!
季節がくれば 黄金の国 輝かすよ
When the season comes, it shines into a golden land!
南はどうだい 北まで行くかい
How is the south? Shall we go to the north?
友情の前線だ 想いがwaveにかわる 愛してる
It's the frontline of friendship, feelings turn into waves, I love you!
最高に最強で 最上の最大で 最愛の未来に 会いに行くから
To the most high, strongest, best, and greatest, to our dearest future we'll go!
最高の笑顔で 迎えてほしいよ
Greet it with your best smiles!
時を越え つなげよう ヒストリー
Connecting through time, the history!
素晴らしい ヒストリー
Wonderful history!
さあ、ポルカが突き抜けるぞ!
Let's go, Polka's climax!
最高に 最強で 最上の 最大で 最愛の 未来に
To the most high, strongest, best, and greatest, to our dearest future we'll go!
最愛の 未来に 会いに行くから 最高に
最高の 笑顔で 迎えてほしいよ
Greet it with your best smiles!
時を越え 舞うのさ ヒストリー
Crossing time, dancing history!
素晴らしい ヒストリー
Wonderful history!
顔で笑って 心で泣いた
With a smile on my face and crying in my heart,
嬉し涙のために 笑顔の種を蒔きましょう
for the tears of joy, let's sow the seeds of smiles!
世界と一緒に踊りましょう 日本がおくるヒット・パレード 花咲かせよう
Let's dance together with the world, Japan's hit parade, let's make flowers bloom!
私たちもまた歌ってゆきたい 何世紀たってもみんなの勇気になれる 歌たちを
We also want to keep singing, songs that can give everyone courage no matter the century!
最高に 最強で 最上の 最大で 最愛の 未来に
To the most high, strongest, best, and greatest, to our dearest future we'll go!
最高の 笑顔で 迎えてほしいよ
Greet it with your best smiles!
時を越え 舞うのさ ヒストリー
Crossing time, dancing history!
最高に 最強で 最上の 最大で 最愛の 未来に
To the most high, strongest, best, and greatest, to our dearest future we'll go!
最高の 笑顔で 迎えてほしいよ
Greet it with your best smiles!
時を超え 繋げよう
Crossing time, let's connect it,
ヒストリー
history!
素晴らしい it's a golden ヒストリー
Wonderful, it's a golden history!
ありがとう 本当に大好きの歌なので
Thank you so much! I really love this song,
すごく感動してます。
so I'm deeply moved.
意気アツをぶちかまします！
Let's unleash our energy!
行くぞ！
Here we go!
最高！ 最強！
The best! The strongest!
it's a golden history 最上！ 最大！
It's a golden history! The highest! The greatest!
it's a golden history 最高！ 最強！
It's a golden history! The best! The strongest!
it's a golden history 最上！ 最大！
It's a golden history! The highest! The greatest!
最高！ 最強！ it's a golden history
The best! The strongest, it's a golden history!
WE CAN GO!!
いくつもの違いを 超えるために
To overcome our many differences
強くなる
and grow stronger,
もう一歩 もう一歩
take one more step, another step,
さあ 先へ進め
and press onward!
最高に 泣けそうな きれいな
It's a dazzling light that
ヒカリだ
almost makes me want to cry,
私が 変われば 明日も 変わる
If I change, tomorrow changes too.
歴史の上を 行く 新しい
Let's leave new footprints
足跡 残そう
on the path of history!
続いてく 真っまっさらな ヒストリー
Continuing on, a brand new history,
歩いてこう ヒストリー
let's walk through it, history!
黄金の国よ 栄え！
O golden land, flourish!
はーい！ ありがとうございましたー！
Hii! Thank you very much!
お聞きくださいましたのは みんなでゴールデン...
What you just listened to was everyone's Golden...
おっと、いない！
Oh wait, nobody's here!
あはは、帰り道が早いな。 えー、じゃあゴールデンヒストリーでした！
Ahaha, the way back is fast. Well then, that was 'The Golden History'!
ポルかもこれ、みんなで前から歌いたかったんだよね。
Polka wanted us all to sing this from the start too.
あとで語らせていただきますが、その前に、えー、尾丸ポルカ 誕生日記念23のグッズ紹介です！
I'll talk more about it later, but before that, here is the introduction for my 2023 birthday merch!
こちらどーん！
Here they are!
というわけでこちら気になる詳細は、えっと、ちょっと待ってください、どっちだどっちだ？
So, as for the details of these items, um, hold on, which is which?
えっとこっちかな？ はい、あってた、よかった。
Um, is it this one? Yes, that's right, phew.
はーい、というわけでこれですね、えっと、1つ目はB2タペストリー！ えーこちら、なんとぎどりあ先生描き下ろしになっております。
Hii, so here is this one, um, first is the B2 Tapestry! This features brand new art drawn by Gidora-sensei.
いいでしょ？ これ、あの、朝のポルカなんやけど、ちょっと、うーん、まあ、若干のフィクションが入っているというか、ポルカこんな朝料理するか、朝早く起きるか？
Isn't it nice? This is morning Polka, but it has a bit of fiction mixed in. Does Polka actually cook breakfast like this or wake up early?
うーん、ちょっとまあ、でも、ちょっと、あの、かっこつけました。 えー、目線はきちんとみんなに向いてるよっていうことで、まあみんなというかお前というか、そういうことっていうか、に向いてるよって感じですね。
Well, but I tried to look a bit cool. The gaze is properly directed toward everyone—well, toward 'you', that kind of thing.
そして2つ目はステッカー！ こちら、もと先生の描き下ろしです！ 絵柄となんと4種類！ えー、めっちゃかわいい！
And the second is stickers! These are illustrated by Moto-sensei! There are four different designs! Super cute!
あの、なんていうの、このちっちゃい、ちっちゃい子ね、ちっちゃい子ね、えー、めちゃいい、便利なステッカーと思います。ステッカーっていんなとこにも貼るからな。よろしくお願いいたします。
Um, these little ones, right? I think they're really convenient stickers. You can stick them in all sorts of places. Thank you very much.
そして3つ目は、はい、どーん！ 書いてある内容がめっちゃ重いんだよねこれ。 ざいんくん証明書。
And the third is, yes, ta-da! The written content is so heavy, seriously. The 'Zain-kun Certificate'.
あのね、すっげえ重いけど、まあ、うん、軽い気持ちでおひとつ買っていかないかね、ねえちゃん？ はい、めちゃ重いです。
You know, it's super heavy, but won't you buy one with a light heart, sis? Yes, it's super heavy.
裏にも、まあ裏は、あのね、ポルカのメッセージが書いてありますので、そちらもよく読むことです！ はい。
On the back too—well, the back has Polka's message written on it, so you should read it thoroughly! Yes.
そして4つ目ですね。 あ、とんだわ。 ごめん、ちがう。こっち！ はい、しっぽクッション、8つめ！ だーん！ 70cm！
And the fourth one. Ah, I skipped ahead. Sorry, wrong one. This one! Yes, the tail cushion! Ta-da! 70 centimeters!
で、しっぽクッションで、あの、どん、なんかね、欲しいてけっこう言われてたんだけど、ようやく作ることができました。このね、ポルカのしっぽのクッションやれ、っていうことで、まあ、大きさ、まあ、70cmでございます。
And for the tail cushion, people kept saying they wanted one, and we were finally able to make it. People said, 'Do Polka's tail cushion!', so the size is 70 centimeters.
で、あの、なんて言えばいいのかな、ワッペンみたいなのがちょっと付いてるんだけど、そこがポルカのオーレジンになる、こうなるところなので、そちらもお楽しみ、家の中なら触りごこっついを楽しみんで
And there's a patch-like thing attached, and that part becomes Polka's aurigin, so please look forward to that too, and enjoy touching it inside your house...
まあ ええと だから、まあ さっき飛ばしました一つ目はシチュエーションボイスになっております。
Well, um, so, anyway, the first one I skipped earlier is a situation voice pack.
ポルカとの何でもない休日、さっきの朝のポスターとリンクしております。
This is linked with the morning poster from earlier, which has no shortage of mornings.
そしてそしてそしてそして！
And then, and then, and then, and then!
こちらのフルセット全部ご購入していただきましたらなんと！
If you purchase all of these full sets,
特典一、おまるポルカ誕生日記念直筆サイン入りどろ先生描き下ろしポストカードの！
Bonus one: Omaru Polka's birthday-exclusive autographed postcard drawn by Teacher Doro!
こちら無制限！
This... Unspecified!
頼まれたら描けるだけ書いちゃうのがおまるポルカ！
Omaru Polka will draw as many as are requested!
ははは！しかもね、ちょっとね、描かれてる表情がすっごくどろ先生にあるずえ！
Haha! And what's more, the expression on Teacher Doro's drawing is so lovely, right?
ええ、この絵本当にポルカ好きなので、ぜひね、まあよかったら全部買ってくれたらいいんじゃないですかね。
Yeah, I really love this drawing, so please, well, if you'd like, buying the whole set would be great, right?
まあ、なんでこんなに推してるかって言うと、さらにさらに！特典二！
So, why am I pushing it so much? That's because, even more... Bonus two!
こちら特典ボイス！
Here is the bonus voice!
もっと一緒に休日、もっと一緒に休日、もっと一緒休日の、がついっておりますゆえ
"Spend more holidays together, spend more holidays together, spend more holidays together" has been added,
先ほどの休日合わせて、ま、ポルカとのね、休日
so matching with the previous holidays, well, Polka's holidays...
それは甘いのかしょっぱいのか一体この料理のようにどんな味がするのかわからないね、どんな味がするんだろうね！
Whether that's sweet or sour, I wonder what kind of taste this cooking has, I have no idea, what kind of taste will it have?
ということになっております！はい、こちらが、えーと、ポルカのグッズすべてになっております！
And that's how it is! Yes, this is all of Polka's merchandise!
とりあえずまあ、まとめるといっぱいグッズ出るよ！
For now, to sum it up, you get a lot of goods!
あ、フルセットも出るよ、サイン付き出るよ、無制限だよ！
You get the full set, you get the autographed one, it's unlimited!
いっぱい、いっぱいあるよ！
There's lots and lots of them!
で、値段などこちら、サイズこちらいっぱい書いてあるよ、詳細などは
And as for prices and sizes, they're all written here,
えー、サイズまで、えー発売はこれから、シュタッグは、こちらもう全部買っといた！
uh, sizes and sales start from now, and for autographed items, I'm going to sign all of them!
よろしくお願いします！
Thank you very much!
あ、あと、えっと、えっと、え、番組の最後には
Ah, also, um, um, at the end of the program,
メンバー限定の配信も一応、あ、初めてやるんだよそれ！
we'll also have a member-limited stream... wait, is this the first time doing that?
ねえ、何すればいいんだろ？何すればいいんだろ？決まってるんだけど、ちょっとあるんで、よろしくお願いいたします。
Hey, what should I do for that? What should I do? It's already decided, but since there's some stuff, please look forward to it!
そして、えー、それだけではもしかしたら終わらないかな、何かが上がるかな？
And then, just with that, maybe it won't be enough, something might come up?
それはお楽しみにしておいて、ください！
Please look forward to that as well!
というわけで、ポルカ、みんながね、あんだけ元気くれたから、もう低気圧にも負けない体をもった気がする。
So, Polka, everyone gave me so much energy, so I feel like I won't lose even to low pressure!
だから最後に、届けたい、その曲、そう。
So at the end, I want to deliver that song, yes.
そう。これどうしようかな。
So, what should I do about this?
曲名言ったらなんか終わりな気がするんだけど、え、つ、え、よ。
Saying the song title makes it feel like it's ending, but... well, yeah.
それでは、あれだけね、みんなにね、支えられましたポルカ、今年1年頑張りたいと思います。
So, just that, everyone, Polka has received your support, so I want to do my best for this whole year!
それでは、ルザー。
Then, loser!
いつもの通りの通り独り
As always, same street, alone
こんな日々もはや懲り懲り
I've had enough of such days
もうどこにも行けやしないのに
Can't go anywhere anymore, still
夢見ておやすみ
Watching dreams, good night
いつでも僕らはこんな風に
Like this we're always
ぼんくらな夜に飽き飽き
Tired, tired of dimwitted nights
また踊り踊り出す明日に
To dance, dance again tomorrow
出会うためにさようなら
We meet again, goodbye
歩き回ってやっと着いた
Walked about forever, finally arrived
ここはどこだ楽園か?
What’s this here, paradise?
今となってもうわからない
I just don't know anymore
四半世紀の結果出た
The result of a quarter century is here
青い顔のスーパースターが
A green-faced superstar
お腹すかせては待っている
Waiting with an empty stomach
アイムアルーザー
I'm a loser
どうせだったら遠吠えだっていいだろう
So might as well howl
もう一回もう一回行こうぜ僕らの声
Once more, once more, raise our voices
アイムアルーザー
I'm a loser
ずっと前から聞こえていた
From way before, the one I heard
いつかポケットに隠した声が
And eventually hid in my pocket, that voice
まあなんえないならどうなったっていいだろう
I don't fucking care
幸先の空は悪天候
The sky of good omens has bad weather
ほら窓から覗いた摩天楼からすりゃ塵のように
See, from a skyscraper window, it looks just like dust
アイアンもカートも昔の人よ
Ian and Curt are the old guard
中指立ててもしょうがないのよ
Showing the finger, whatcha gonna do
今勝ち上がるためのお勉強廊下な表情
Serves as a lesson to get ahead now, cheerful face
踊る阿呆に見る阿呆
Idiots watch idiots dance
我らそれを端から笑う阿呆
And us idiots laughing from the sideline
デカイ自意識抱え込んではもう磨耗
Clinging to a huge ego just leads to abrasion
すり減って残る酸っぱい葡萄
Wearing you down till there's only sour grapes
膝抱えてもなんにもねえ
Hugging your knees ain't helping either
ほら長い前髪で前が見えねえ
See, you can't see what's ahead with your long hair
いつもどおりの通り独り
As always, same street, alone,
こんな日々もはや懲り懲り
I've had enough of such days.
もうどこにも行けやしないのに
Can't go anywhere anymore, still
夢見ておやすみ
watching dreams, good night.
いつでも僕らはこんな風に
Like this, we're always
ぼんくらな夜に飽き飽き
tired, tired of dimwitted nights.
また踊り踊り出す明日に
To dance, dance again tomorrow
出会うためにさよなら
and meet the new day, goodbye.
歩き回ってやっと着いた
Walked about forever, finally arrived.
ここはどこだ楽園か？
What's this here, paradise?
今となってもうわからない
I just don't know anymore.
四半世紀の結果出た
The result of a quarter century is here,
青い顔のスーパースターが
a green-faced superstar
お腹すかして待っている
waiting with an empty stomach.
アイエムルーザー
I'm a loser.
どうせだったら遠吠えだっていいだろう
So might as well howl at the distance.
もう一回もう一回行こうぜ僕らの声
Once more, once more, raise our voices!
アイエムルーザー ずっと前から聞こえてた
I'm a loser, from way before I heard it,
いつかポケットに隠した声が
that voice I hid in my pocket someday.
幸先の空は悪天候
The sky of good omens has bad weather.
ほら窓から覗いた摩天楼
See, from a skyscraper window,
からすりゃ塵のよう
it looks just like dust.
イアンもカートも昔の人よ
Ian and Kurt are the old guard.
中指立ててもしょうがないの
Showing the finger changes nothing.
今勝ち上がるためのお勉強
Just studying to get ahead now.
朗らかな表情
With a cheerful expression,
踊る阿呆に見る阿呆
idiots watch idiots dance,
我らそれを端から笑う阿呆
and us idiots laughing from the sideline.
デカイ自意識抱え込んでは
Clinging to a huge ego
もう摩耗
just leads to abrasion.
すり減って残る酸っぱい葡萄
Worn down to sour grapes.
膝抱えてもなんもねえ
Hugging your knees helps nothing.
ほら長い前髪で前が見えねえ
See, you can't see ahead with long hair.
笑っちまうねパッと沸き立って
It's too funny, popping up instantly
ふ和っと消えちまうこんな輪廻
and vanishing in this cycle of rebirth.
愛されたいならそう言おうぜ
Say it if you wanna be loved.
想ってるだけじゃ伝わらないね
Nobody gets it if you just think it.
永遠の淑女もそっぽ向いて
Even the eternal lady turns away,
天国は遠く向こうの方へ
and paradise is far away over there.
ああわかってるって深く転がる俺は負け犬
Yeah, I know, tumbling deep down, I'm a loser.
ただどこでもいいから遠くへ行きたいんだ
I just wanna go anywhere far away, that's all.
それだけなんだ
That's really all.
耳をすませ遠くで今鳴り出した音を逃すな
Listen closely to the sound ringing out far away.
呼吸を整えて
Ready your breath,
いつかは出会えるはずの黄金色のアイオライト
and you'll surely meet the golden iolite.
きっと掴んで離すな
Catch it and never let go.
アイエムルーザー
I'm a loser.
どうせだったら遠吠えだっていいだろう
So might as well howl at the distance.
もう一回もう一回行こうぜ僕らの声
Once more, once more, raise our voices!
アイエムルーザー
I'm a loser.
ずっと前から聞こえてた
From way before, I could hear
いつかポケットに隠した声が
that voice I once hid in my pocket.
ここいらでひとつ踊ってみようぜ
Since we're here, let's have a dance.
夜が明けるまで転がっていこうぜ
Let's roll around until dawn breaks.
聞こえてるなら声出していこうぜ
If you can hear this, raise your voice.
アイエムルーザー
I'm a loser.
どうせだったら遠吠えだっていいだろう
So might as well howl at the distance.
もう一回もう一回行こうぜ僕らの声
Once more, once more, raise our voices!
アイエムルーザー
I'm a loser.
ずっと前から聞こえてた
From way before, I could hear
いつかポケットに隠した声が
that voice I once hid in my pocket.